<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title><!--Fill in a title--></title>
            <author><!--Fill in the author--></author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent><!--fill in the extent--></extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>Tufts University Digital Collections and Archives</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Tufts University</addrLine>
               <addrLine>35 Professors Row</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Tisch Library Medford, MA 01255</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno><!--fill in the ID number--></idno>
            <availability status="free">
               <p>This publication is freely available for scholarly or educational use.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <recordingStmt>
               <recording type="audio" dur="6869472ms">
                  <date><!--Fill in the date of the _recording_--></date>
                  <equipment>
                     <p><!--Fill in details about the recoring equipment--></p>
                  </equipment>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>interview conducted by:</resp>
                     <name><!--Fill in the person responsable for the recording--></name>
                  </respStmt>
               </recording>
            </recordingStmt>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <stdVals>
               <p>Standard date values are given in ISO form: yyyy-mm-dd.</p>
            </stdVals>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy id="LCSH">
               <bibl>
                  <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy id="LC">
               <bibl>
                  <title>Library of Congress</title>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <date><!--Fill in an appropriate creation date (for the transcript)--></date>
         </creation>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="EN" usage="100">English.</language>
         </langUsage>
         <particDesc>
           <person id="KM" role="lecturer" sex="m"><p>Kris Manjapra</p></person>
           <person id="RK" role="lecturer" sex="m"><p>Robert Kaplan</p></person>         
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <timeline id="transcript_timeline" unit="millisecond" origin="timepoint_begin">
            <when id="timepoint_begin" absolute="beginning of recording"/>
            <when id="timepoint_1" since="timepoint_begin" interval="0"/>
            <when id="timepoint_2" since="timepoint_begin" interval="80900"/>
            <when id="timepoint_3" since="timepoint_begin" interval="153100"/>
            <when id="timepoint_4" since="timepoint_begin" interval="218400"/>
            <when id="timepoint_5" since="timepoint_begin" interval="298500"/>
            <when id="timepoint_6" since="timepoint_begin" interval="376100"/>
            <when id="timepoint_7" since="timepoint_begin" interval="433600"/>
            <when id="timepoint_8" since="timepoint_begin" interval="472600"/>
            <when id="timepoint_8" since="timepoint_begin" interval="535100"/>
            <when id="timepoint_9" since="timepoint_begin" interval="623600"/>
            <when id="timepoint_10" since="timepoint_begin" interval="674400"/>
            <when id="timepoint_11" since="timepoint_begin" interval="720100"/>
            <when id="timepoint_12" since="timepoint_begin" interval="813400"/>
            <when id="timepoint_13" since="timepoint_begin" interval="867200"/>
            <when id="timepoint_14" since="timepoint_begin" interval="956800"/>
            <when id="timepoint_15" since="timepoint_begin" interval="1041800"/>
            <when id="timepoint_16" since="timepoint_begin" interval="1113500"/>
            <when id="timepoint_17" since="timepoint_begin" interval="1197700"/>
            <when id="timepoint_18" since="timepoint_begin" interval="1280700"/>
            <when id="timepoint_19" since="timepoint_begin" interval="1342600"/>
            <when id="timepoint_20" since="timepoint_begin" interval="1416700"/>
            <when id="timepoint_21" since="timepoint_begin" interval="1502700"/>
            <when id="timepoint_22" since="timepoint_begin" interval="1592300"/>
            <when id="timepoint_23" since="timepoint_begin" interval="1628500"/>
            <when id="timepoint_24" since="timepoint_begin" interval="1690900"/>
            <when id="timepoint_25" since="timepoint_begin" interval="1760900"/>
            <when id="timepoint_26" since="timepoint_begin" interval="1820500"/>
            <when id="timepoint_27" since="timepoint_begin" interval="1889300"/>
            <when id="timepoint_28" since="timepoint_begin" interval="1977300"/>
            <when id="timepoint_29" since="timepoint_begin" interval="2018900"/>
            <when id="timepoint_30" since="timepoint_begin" interval="2095300"/>
            <when id="timepoint_31" since="timepoint_begin" interval="2162600"/>
            <when id="timepoint_32" since="timepoint_begin" interval="2251600"/>
            <when id="timepoint_33" since="timepoint_begin" interval="2340300"/>
            <when id="timepoint_34" since="timepoint_begin" interval="2394000"/>
            <when id="timepoint_35" since="timepoint_begin" interval="2441000"/>
            <when id="timepoint_36" since="timepoint_begin" interval="2538200"/>
            <when id="timepoint_37" since="timepoint_begin" interval="2645800"/>
            <when id="timepoint_38" since="timepoint_begin" interval="2712700"/>
            <when id="timepoint_39" since="timepoint_begin" interval="2787700"/>
            <when id="timepoint_40" since="timepoint_begin" interval="2856300"/>
            <when id="timepoint_41" since="timepoint_begin" interval="2915600"/>
            <when id="timepoint_42" since="timepoint_begin" interval="2975700"/>
            <when id="timepoint_43" since="timepoint_begin" interval="3053400"/>
            <when id="timepoint_44" since="timepoint_begin" interval="3132800"/>
            <when id="timepoint_45" since="timepoint_begin" interval="3201400"/>
            <when id="timepoint_46" since="timepoint_begin" interval="3259300"/>
            <when id="timepoint_46 a" since="timepoint_begin" interval="3319700"/>
            <when id="timepoint_47" since="timepoint_begin" interval="3404800"/>
            <when id="timepoint_48" since="timepoint_begin" interval="3473100"/>
            <when id="timepoint_" since="timepoint_begin" interval="3577200"/>
            <when id="timepoint_48" since="timepoint_begin" interval="3577200"/>
            <when id="timepoint_49" since="timepoint_begin" interval="3668500"/>
            <when id="timepoint_50" since="timepoint_begin" interval="3732900"/>
            <when id="timepoint_51" since="timepoint_begin" interval="3822300"/>
            <when id="timepoint_52" since="timepoint_begin" interval="3916100"/>
            <when id="timepoint_53" since="timepoint_begin" interval="4009200"/>
            <when id="timepoint_54" since="timepoint_begin" interval="4058000"/>
            <when id="timepoint_55" since="timepoint_begin" interval="4102400"/>
            <when id="timepoint_56" since="timepoint_begin" interval="4206000"/>
            <when id="timepoint_57" since="timepoint_begin" interval="4253800"/>
            <when id="timepoint_58" since="timepoint_begin" interval="4307700"/>
            <when id="timepoint_59" since="timepoint_begin" interval="4349000"/>
            <when id="timepoint_60" since="timepoint_begin" interval="4381300"/>
            <when id="timepoint_61" since="timepoint_begin" interval="4439200"/>
            <when id="timepoint_62" since="timepoint_begin" interval="4501500"/>
            <when id="timepoint_63" since="timepoint_begin" interval="4597300"/>
            <when id="timepoint_64" since="timepoint_begin" interval="4656900"/>
            <when id="timepoint_65" since="timepoint_begin" interval="4744500"/>
            <when id="timepoint_66" since="timepoint_begin" interval="4841000"/>
            <when id="timepoint_67" since="timepoint_begin" interval="4912700"/>
            <when id="timepoint_69" since="timepoint_begin" interval="4996100"/>
            <when id="timepoint_70" since="timepoint_begin" interval="5027100"/>
            <when id="timepoint_71" since="timepoint_begin" interval="5091200"/>
            <when id="timepoint_72" since="timepoint_begin" interval="5140300"/>
            <when id="timepoint_73" since="timepoint_begin" interval="5201100"/>
            <when id="timepoint_74" since="timepoint_begin" interval="5259000"/>
            <when id="timepoint_75" since="timepoint_begin" interval="5341300"/>
            <when id="timepoint_76" since="timepoint_begin" interval="5419800"/>
            <when id="timepoint_77" since="timepoint_begin" interval="5467000"/>
            <when id="timepoint_78" since="timepoint_begin" interval="5498300"/>
            <when id="timepoint_79" since="timepoint_begin" interval="5610100"/>
            <when id="timepoint_80" since="timepoint_begin" interval="5662300"/>
            <when id="timepoint_81" since="timepoint_begin" interval="5725900"/>
            <when id="timepoint_82" since="timepoint_begin" interval="5776299"/>
            <when id="timepoint_83" since="timepoint_begin" interval="5852200"/>
            <when id="timepoint_84" since="timepoint_begin" interval="5903900"/>
            <when id="timepoint_85" since="timepoint_begin" interval="6020700"/>
            <when id="timepoint_86" since="timepoint_begin" interval="6078700"/>
            <when id="timepoint_88" since="timepoint_begin" interval="6153000"/>
            <when id="timepoint_89" since="timepoint_begin" interval="6258700"/>
            <when id="timepoint_84" since="timepoint_begin" interval="6312600"/>
            <when id="timepoint_85" since="timepoint_begin" interval="6385000"/>
            <when id="timepoint_86" since="timepoint_begin" interval="6405700"/>
            <when id="timepoint_87" since="timepoint_begin" interval="6479600"/>
            <when id="timepoint_88" since="timepoint_begin" interval="6532600"/>
            <when id="timepoint_89" since="timepoint_begin" interval="6581400"/>
            <when id="timepoint_90" since="timepoint_begin" interval="6622900"/>
            <when id="timepoint_91" since="timepoint_begin" interval="6688300"/>
            <when id="timepoint_92" since="timepoint_begin" interval="6771800"/>
            <when id="timepoint_end" since="timepoint_begin" interval="6869472"/>
         </timeline>
         <div1 id="transcript.1" n="Transcript">
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_1" n="1" end="timepoint_2">
<u who="KM">My name is Kris Manjapra and I am an Assistant Professor here at the Tufts University in the History Department and it&#8217;s my great pleasure and honour to be the chairperson for this semester series for our lecture series at the Centre for South Asian Indian Ocean studies at Tufts. This year beginning last fall as Professor Ayesha Jalal who is the Director of the centre was still in residence with us we began a series called Islam on the Indian Ocean rim and this semester continues that theme we have had a number of illustrious speakers and  semesters and in fact we are on the up and up as this afternoon or this evening we have with us tremendously articulate imaginative and influential thinker public intellectual journalists and really one might also say that an academic given how academically informed his scholarship is and also how well read he is within academia and respected and of course,I am speaking of Robert Kaplan. </u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_2" n="2" end="timepoint_3">
<u>We have a special event because in some ways it is a special feature because Robert Kaplan is here with us along with Professor Saugata Bose who I would also like to thank very much for his contributions to the discussions that&#8217;s going to happen.I just want to just very briefly introduce both Robert Kaplan and then Saugata Bose and give a brief kind of blue print of how the discussion will work because we are hoping to have a conversation that will also involve the audience and then turn it over to our guests. So, Robert Kaplan is a national correspondent for the Atlantic and senior fellow at the centre for a new American security in Washington D.C. and it&#8217;s really his long and illustrious career including at least 12 books many of them have been on the list best selling list over the last sort of 3 decades in fact but it&#8217;s really his latest book in fact Monsoon the Indian Ocean and the future of America power published in 2010 that this discussion will revolve around.</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_3" n="3" end="timepoint_4">
<u>You know when I think of Robert Kaplan&#8217;s work, I think perhaps even of Iban Batuta or I think of Alexander Von Humboldt  or I think of Thessegar some of the great travelling intellectuals of not only our times but also of earlier times and the kind of ability to provide a synoptic overview as well as great detail about some of the most important changes that are geo politically taking place in our world today so that is the theme kind of gathers us here.Saugata Bose, Professor Bose is the gardener professor Of Oceanic History at Harvard University and he also is serving at a special capacity over this year and in coming years as the Chairperson for the mentor group at the Presidency University in Calcutta an important role that involved restructuring education in Bengal. </u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_4" n="4" end="timepoint_5">
<u>Professor Bose is the author of many, many influential books path breaking books for our field and beyond the field as South Asian studies and most recently his majesty&#8217;s opponent Subhas Chandra Bose and India&#8217;s struggle against Empire which came out with Harvard University Press in 2011 so as not to extend you know my voice too far in the evening&#8217;s proceedings let me cut short and let me say that it&#8217;s really an honour to have two global thinkers who know the Indian Ocean world so well who can speak about what Robert Kaplan so eloquently calls the Rim land of the Indian Ocean and it&#8217;s import for world politics with us today. In terms of how we will proceed we asked Robert whether he might first provide a 20 perhaps 30 minute introduction to his work to some of the themes of his book and then there would be a kind of free flowing conversation between Robert and Saugata and following that we will open it up to the audience for further discussion so having said all of that may I hand it over to you.</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_5" n="5" end="timepoint_6">
<u who="RK">well thank you it&#8217;s really a great privilege and honour to be here Saugata&#8217;s book a Hundred horizons helped and inspired me to write my own book so it&#8217;s you know though it&#8217;s kind of a double feature for me too and I have his book on hard copy by the way and let me start this way you know in Washington everyone wants to reduce things the policy terms and people kept asking me at the Presidency and the national security Affairs what&#8217;s your strategy going to be for the Indian Ocean and my response was that we don&#8217;t have a strategy, it&#8217;s a concept it&#8217;s not a strategy and it&#8217;s a concept because it helps you to unite the world, the world the greater middle east and the world on the Western Pacific because we think that we are too much prisoners of cold war in various studies where we separate out the globe or Asia particularly into artificial divisions of the middle Central Asia, South Asia, South east Asia, East Asia and so forth.</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_6" n="6" end="timepoint_7">
<u>And what the Indian ocean as a concept allows you to do is think organically in terms of the fluid organic continual whereby the middle east does all this trade with China for instance and in our day all the energy the oil and the natural gas is in the greater middle east in the Arabian Peninsula and the Arabian plato and the customers are increasingly in the middle class of coastal China, south Korea, Japan and so and the Indian Ocean is the great connector, it&#8217;s the inter State it&#8217;s the global high way interstate in this maritime world where despite jet and information age 90% of all commercial goods that travel inter continentally do so by sea. </u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_7" n="7" end="timepoint_8">
<u>You know this symbol of the global aid is actually the super taker either an oil super taker or one of those big ships with like a thousand containers on that you see so the Indian Ocean I said to Washington policy makers allows you to think more creatively allows you to think of your Asia as just one united Rim land you know the navigable Southern rim land and because the Northern rim land of your Asia is all I spot you know in North of Russia. </u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_8" n="8" end="timepoint_8">
<u>So we have been prisoners of cold war studies, Americans have been the prisoners of 8.00 projection which puts North and South America in the Centre and splits up the pacific and Indian Ocean and the edges and therefore the edges of consciousness and what the Indian Ocean allows us to do is to see the world whole and to see really it&#8217;s centre over the next few decades because by 2050 there&#8217;s going to be about 9 Billion people in the world and 7 of those 9 Billion are going to be living vaguely around on the Indian Ocean Rim Land the greater Indian Ocean Rim Land taken if you put together the populations of east Asia, South East Asia, South Asia, the middle east what you have got there is almost 7 of 9 Billion people of the world </u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_8" n="8" end="timepoint_9">
<u>so the Indian Ocean is the unifier it&#8217;s the centre of the map for the 21st century in that sense the centre of conflict and a centre also of trade and cultural relations and my theme you know to me it&#8217;s what the most unique and relevant thing for our century about the Indian Ocean is the monsoon because the monsoon winds more than any other wind path over nor predictable you know blowing North east, south, west then reversing themselves by a 180 degrees south, west and north east and of course with a lot of small variations inside the Bay of Bengal and others but nevertheless because of the predictability of this wind system it allows sailors to calculate sailing times in advance and thus the Indian Ocean did not have to the age of steam ships you know we see united back in the 18th medieval era remember when Vasco-da-gama sailed from what is today&#8217;s Kenya to what is today&#8217;s south west India, half the distance of the Indian Ocean thousands of miles he did it in 23 days which is an amazing feat if any of you or your parents are recreational sailors you should know this.</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_9" n="9" end="timepoint_10">
<u>and he was able to do this not because he discovered the wind system or the Portuguese didn&#8217;t discover it was the medieval era who re acquainted them with it. Re acquainted them with it because the Romans and the Greeks may have known about it you know to a large extent you know if you hunt down the estuary in Bengal you may find some Roman coins you know or some Greek coins because the Romans and the Greeks got that far and so because of the monsoon winds because it did not have to wait for the age of the steam ships to unite it you know you have the remains of the 8th century mosques in China you have large Malay communities from the East Indies in Madagasca just off the coast of East Africa. </u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_10" n="10" end="timepoint_11">
<u>You have Almanis all along the coast of East Africa, you have Gujarati&#8217;s from North West India all over the Indian Ocean map, You have Yemeni&#8217;s in Indonesia you know significant populations everywhere with, everyone with everywhere because in the cultural sense because of the wind system it was a united community and so there was like a unifying element in the medieval era that policy makers today would do well to study because it is quite relevant how well they can conceive of a whole Eurasian trade and security system.</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_11" n="11" end="timepoint_12">
<u>Another thing that the Indian Ocean does is it allows you to think of Islam not as a dessert religion but spread relatively, quickly by the sword across the sands of North Africa but spread very gradually over the course of the centuries by sophisticated merchants in ships, I just got back from Malaysia for instance I spend a month in Malaysia and Singapore and its fascinating you know Malaysia may be one of the most influential countries in the Muslim world in terms of where Islam is going because Malaysians a democracy been so for quite a few decades not a perfect one by any means we can study that and it&#8217;s also one of the most technologically developed countries in the world so it&#8217;s become a high tech functioning democracy where 60% of the country are Muslims and interact with 20% ethnic Chinese and another 9% who are Indians and this is all the residue of the monsoon wind system merchants of gradual conversions over the course of centuries and we can talk similarly about Indonesia and other places </u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_12" n="12" end="timepoint_13">
<u>and as I said we are going back to a classical super region. It&#8217;s possible that in the course of the next few decades we will see canals and land bridge projects connecting the Bay of Bengal with South China Sea being as energy prices go up if you can consider that global energy demand is going to go up by almost 50% over the next 20 &#8211; 30 years half of that&#8217;s going to come from India and China even with Chinese growth slowing down you are entering a world with where there are going to be more consumers more middle class consumers for energy and goods and that is going to mean a sea a straight of Malaika a straight of sudamacassa and Lomba and one more crowded with ships</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_13" n="13" end="timepoint_14">
<u>and you are going to need other so the Malaysians are exploring land bridge projects across the Peninsular Malaysia there&#8217;s renewed talk about a proper canal across the so that the Indian Ocean proper and the South China Sea are going to be liable and much more organic in terms of their relations with each other in the course of the coming decades and the South China Sea let me tell you is there we have got more than half of the world merchant fleet tiny age a third of all maritime traffic world wide the oil transport through the Malaika straight from the Indian Ocean with the South China Sea is triple the amount that passes Sewers canal and fifteen times the amount that pass the Panama canal so we are really talking about you know the nerve centre you know the real coagulated nerve centre of the world, of Eurasia going forward and the real drama here this strategic drama is that the West is gradually ever so gradually receding and indigenous powers arrive.</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_14" n="14" end="timepoint_15">
<u>Globalization is about navies and air Force&#8217;s much more than about marine and army corps because navy&#8217;s and air force you know help protect sea lines communication. They project power and they often have peace keeping functions that armies and Marine Corps you know there&#8217;s an old saying that armies convey navies make port visits and it&#8217;s really true in a way. The American navies platoing size make it even smaller, it&#8217;s gone down from almost 600 ships in 1980&#8217;s to less than 300 hundred ships war ships today. It&#8217;s unclear if they sustain themselves as these numbers going forward over the next 20 or 30 years meanwhile India and China are growing dramatically bigger navies. You know china will have more sub marines afloat than United States navy in about 15 years and China is not just developing these quite diesel electric sub marines but nuclear sub marines which means that China has blue water oceanic ambitions because you only build or develop nuclear sub marines if you want to operate in the great Ocean&#8217;s.</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_15" n="15" end="timepoint_16">
<u>Because what nuclear power does it means that you don&#8217;t have to refuel. You are only limited by the amount of food to can carry which is about 90 days on a sub marine so China is developing a great navy and air force much as the united States did at the turn of the 20th century when United States became a great power for the first time and the United States suddenly had trading interests all over the world and dug the Panama Canal and built a great navy in order to protect those interests and China seems to be following very much American pattern in that regard. There&#8217;s a lot of details I can go into about everything that China&#8217;s doing with it you know cyber warfare capabilities its fourth and fifth generations fighter jets you know it&#8217;s in large fleets of vessels but they are very serious about ultimately protecting their own sea lines of communication not being dependent on the American navy for this.</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_16" n="16" end="timepoint_17">
<u>India&#8217;s navy over the last few decades going forward is also increasing by leaps and bounds and it&#8217;s not just them the increase in defence spending Vietnam, Malaysia, Singapore is astounding, it&#8217;s all I mean it&#8217;s the submarines or the new blinks everybody wants more you know some countries are not sure about what to do with them but they are buying and they are training groups. Japan and South Korea continue to modernize their fleets so there&#8217;s a trend here which is indigenous powers taking control of the region gradually in a very military sense and while the American navy and Air force will continue to dominate it&#8217;s going to be a far more subtle deeper situation you know if the present trend continues and the only thing that can stop present trends frankly is if China were to undergo such a profound socio economic political crisis that would impinge upon their developments projects and that is not likely.  </u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_17" n="17" end="timepoint_18">
<u>China will have a profound socio economic crisis but probably not deep enough and in a direction that would in the rising defence budgets and so this is the post direct Afghanistan world going forward and if it&#8217;s a peaceful world bee taken centrally also whish brings pipelines going from Central Asia into the Indian Ocean region. You know china is the sort of moving vertically South along the Indian Ocean you know financing port projects in Pakistan, Sri Lanka, and Burma and lately in Kenya and lamo in Kenya instead of Sri Lanka, all of these port projects tell a different story the one in Gawadar in Pakistan is a great beautiful port that I have seen but it&#8217;s a kind of road to nowhere at the moment because of security concerns that the Chinese are going forward the one in Burma is not a road to nowhere that is taking its national gas from the Bay of Bengal and transporting in roads and pipelines across central and northern Burma in the southern China and province within a number of years.</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_18" n="18" end="timepoint_19">
<u>The port in Sri Lanka that they are building is quite impressive and you know and comes in at a time when Chinese influences Sri Lanka is greater never before because of the help China gave Sri Lanka Sri Lankan regime in winning the civil war, China has hopes to transport world from across southern Sudan and Kenya and that again might be for the sky project given the instability between and the fighting between Sudan proper and South Sudan. I was in Beijing for 2 weeks in December meeting with people about this and you know Chinese would say to me well it&#8217;s just that our companies who are doing this, we just have a peaceful commercial purpose along the Indian Ocean and my response was that&#8217;s what the Americans said a thousand years ago. </u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_19" n="19" end="timepoint_20">
<u>People don&#8217;t sit around the table and say now we are going to start an Empire, Empire&#8217;s happen in your sleep so to speak you know they begin as commercial ventures or for specific legitimate purposes and then they grow and expand if they did itself question continues to become dynamic and to the world and so it begins its commercial ventures like an expedition against piracy along Venuses northern Adriatic on the Adriatic coast of the former Yugoslavia in a thousand AD Venice started to establish a commercial  colonies. You know 200 years later Venice you know controls the whole of eastern mediterainean so we will see where these port projects go within the next few decades you know where will be China remember the British east India Company the Dutch east India Company began it&#8217;s purely commercial venture and evolved into much grandeur details in that sense.</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_20" n="20" end="timepoint_21">
<u>India is also expanding horizontally along the Indian Ocean developing you know India will not go along with the US in terms of embargoing around they are going to continue to do business with Iran because they need the natural gas that around too so India is also building pipeline in Burma you know this way to transport the natural gas in the Bay of Bengal through Bangladesh to West Bengal and India and around Bangladesh and again I think one of the exiting developments as I finish my book is the opening up of Burma.The opening up of Burma if it progresses and that is a big if because Burma is not a question of snapping your finger holding an election it&#8217;s really about ethnic reconciliation and you know ending a low level you know fighting between the Burman and the army and the various ethnic irregular forces around the horseshoe of the valley but if Burma can truly open up that could liberate the North East India the chicken bone of India which is being cut off by geographical isolation and a hilly and somewhat mountainous demography in parts.</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_21" n="21" end="timepoint_22">
<u>And so then it&#8217;s small resurgence underdevelopment but with the developed with an opening of Burma and 25.08 and other areas the North east India could finally be liberated you know Burma rather than a place for India and China competing fight over for commercial advantage could become a pulsing centre of trade in itself. There&#8217;s a good book written about that just came out recently in India and Burma meet and which said just a travel book but it go there&#8217;s quite some depth so if you think of Burma opening up and you think 20 years ahead with a stable Afghanistan hopefully a stable Pakistan you have a world of routes and pipelines connecting inner and southern Eurasia to the sea in many different directions where you have recreation of the tang Empire for the 9th century from China doing more and more trade with Iran through central Asia you know how people have this silly argument is it is Eurasia&#8217;s development is going to be by land by sea it&#8217;s going to be both.You know it&#8217;s very much going to be both.</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_22" n="22" end="timepoint_23">
<u>and so I think that this is really going to be a developing, pulsing area that is not going to be easily divided into cold war area studies and war because the inter connections between the various parts of the Indian Ocean Rim the greater Indian Ocean Rim Land from the Middle East to the Western Pacific are going to continue to develop and be vast and I will stop here and thank you.</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_23" n="23" end="timepoint_24">
<u who="SB">so that we can have a conversation, I don&#8217;t intend to offer a long commentary but I think we&#8217;ll let us just see it as a conversation. First of all Thank you for providing such a wonderful summary of the few of the issues that you had raised in your book and you know I really admire your book not just for the writing but here is one strategic analyst who had actually read all the scholarly literature on the Indian Ocean which is very rare you know and which is why you know there&#8217;s such a depth of analysis in Monsoon. </u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_24" n="24" end="timepoint_25">
<u>Let me begin by raising sort of a large questions about the relations between Oceans and Continents I do that because you know this particular project Islam on the Indian Ocean rim is I think is very imaginatively conceived, at one level it takes the  vast Indian Ocean as it&#8217;s campus and explores all of the connections across this Ocean, economic, cultural, political but then the project seeks to two river valley&#8217;s or deltas, the Indus valley on either side of the border that&#8217;s the great India and Pakistan and the Ganges delta on either sides of the borders of Bangladesh and India. So I would like to start by looking at the sort of the big picture the vast canvas first and then perhaps look at these particular river valley&#8217;s and deltas which are connected to the larger Indian Ocean world.</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_25" n="25" end="timepoint_26">
<u>My own sense is that and here is something that you suggested to at the end of your remarks that continents and Oceans you know Asia and the Indian Ocean are conceptually not in an adversarial relationship. I think it is important to underscore how old oceanic connections have been and how important they continue to be as you emphasize 90% of the commodities still travel by ships. On the other hand there always have been very deep of course this is a concept of that 30.02 who has written this book &#8220;The Mediterranean&#8221; showing how in fact there were narrow land which connected the Mediterranean world with Russia, Poland, Germany, France and so on</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_26" n="26" end="timepoint_27">
<u>And so in the case of the Indian Ocean and Asia as well I think there are these land connections in inter regional arenas can be connected by Oceanic flows on the other hand there could be some other important land routes often going from the ports deep into the interior of the continents and this was in some ways brought home to me in a recent trip to China in October I travelled from Kolkata by air to Kurning which is the capital of Unan province in Southern China and it&#8217;s actually such a short distance it was a 2 hour flight and people are beginning to talk about K2K, Kolkata to Kurning connection. From Kurning, I took another flight another 2 hours to Shiyan the capital of Tan dynasty china and there of course I saw one of the mosques that you were eluding to the great Shiyan mosque going back to the 740&#8217;s.</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_27" n="27" end="timepoint_28">
<u>Mosque constructed in a Chinese architectural style but with Arabic calligraphy and clearly here was a city Shiyan which was at the eastern end of trade routes that connected the Arab world, the Persian world, the Indian world with China now these clearly had been land connections. Shiyan is so far from both the Indian Ocean and the Pacific but also in addition to the Presidency University which Kris mentioned I am involved in an effort to re-establish an Asian International University at Nalanda which was the oldest University in the world and flourished from the 5th to the 12th centuries but if you look at the scholar pilgrims who came in from China, Korea, Japan, South east Asia the most famous ones sometimes came by Sea, Eijing came you know via Sumatra  and learnt Sanskrit there and then arrived and then went back by land you know other famous pilgrims came by land went back by sea and then Shyian of course in addition to the great Shiyan mosque I saw the old goose  or rather the big goose Bagoda which is associated with Xuan-Xan who had been in Nalanda in the 7th century as a teacher.</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_28" n="28" end="timepoint_29">
<u>So I was just wondering as you pointed out you know the Indian Ocean is a concept you know that&#8217;s what one has to recognize one can&#8217;t devise strategy in relation to separate bits of that world in old areas that studies small but given what&#8217;s going to be happening in Afghanistan and Central Asia how do you see the links between the Indian Ocean world and you know the continental interiors of Asia playing out?  </u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_29" n="29" end="timepoint_30">
<u who="RK">First of all thanks for that lovely compliment and when you said about the Gangetic plane and the Indian Ocean I thought of Amitabh Ghosh&#8217;s recent novel at the opium trade you know look at the geography of the opium trade which takes you from the central Ganges down to the Bay of Bengal by ship up in to China and the opium trade was just another trade route essentially the same way in fact drugs come from Mexico all along age old trade routes in to the united States the same trade route that kerning now use that is in his expeditions of discovery in the 16th century so i think it&#8217;s fascinating to think in terms of like the Gangetic plane coming down to the Bay Of Bengal and the Indus river valley coming down close to the Arabian sea and you know people there&#8217;s this clich&#233; that Pakistan is artificial in the sense that no it&#8217;s not.</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_30" n="30" end="timepoint_31">
<u>It&#8217;s in Indus valley nation which is you know a very much set up in the ink block of demography which had been in the centre of previous Empires whether it is Ghaznavid or rather going back in to History you know the whole area of all Hind that Andre wink writes about in his book so you have from the Indian Ocean emanating outwork you have the Ganges river valley you have the Indus river valley you have the erewadi river valley and these are path ways in to the interiors that in turn at the head of those path ways connect into central Asia because take Punjab for instance you know Punjab is in the heart of Indus valley civilization in the northern heart.</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_31" n="31" end="timepoint_32">
<u>It&#8217;s the closest real demographic hub to southern central Asia so it reach&#8217;s up into Northern Afghanistan and the southern former southern Saudi union and reaches down Indus valley all the way to Karachi and then into the wider world and thee wider sea and it&#8217;s increasing and it crosses many what in the historical sense or artificial states in the sense that all states are artificial I mean where do you draw the line borders anywhere and I think the biggest drama over the coming years Chinese growth rate we know is going to come down to about 7% but that&#8217;s still 7% that&#8217;s still a lot compared to our own. It&#8217;s going to be how China reaches&#8217; out in to all these regions through trade and as you said it&#8217;s also a 2 hours flight from Kolkata to Kurning you know imagine all the rounds across Burma and through North east India that will make it in about 20 years a comfortable land trip along you know highways </u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_32" n="32" end="timepoint_33">
<u who="SB">You know let&#8217;s talk a little bit more about china you know of course you know reading Amitabh Ghosh&#8217;s novel Sea of Poppies,  you know there&#8217;s this wonderful image of Sacrey Reed the son of a maryled free women who travels on the ship the IBIs and its only after he reaches the Hooghly river that he meets the owner of this black bata which has been refitted a man called Ben Burnham and Ben Burnham tells Sacrey Reed that this ship is not going to be used on its first voyage to carry opium to China from the Gangetic delta because the Chinese are still having problems having the benefits of free trade but then it will be a different kind of a cargo and of course sacrey Reed is quite concerned that you mean you know you are going to use it to carry slaves haven&#8217;t your laws actually abolished that trade and of course Ben Burgham relies yes the laws sort of have done so  but there is going to be this coolie trade because you know when the doors of freedom are close to one people then Africans it&#8217;s gets open to the Asiatic and so then</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_33" n="33" end="timepoint_34">
<u>and so you know there was an Indian Ocean connection even in the 19th century which transformed the older tie across the Indian Ocean because this was a connection of opium between India and China of Indian labourers from India from that same sort of Gangeteic heartland of Bihar and UP to support Mauritius and the Indian heart of the Indian Ocean world but you know coming back to China I think you are absolutely right that what has been new in the contemporary phase of globalization is China&#8217;s decision after a hiatus of several hundred years since the times of Jan hay to project it&#8217;s power economic as well as naval military in the Indian Ocean</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_34" n="34" end="timepoint_35">
<u>so is it your sense that it is the writing and publication of &#8216;Monsoon&#8217; the Chinese leadership has become rather more aggressive and assertive than they have been because there was always a sense of that the Chinese leadership is very pragmatic it did not want to take steps too early that might in fact upset the United States of America but in relation to the South China Sea be certainly but also in terms of its presence in many of the areas that they are building infrastructure in ports and in the Indian Ocean do you see a new assertiveness on the part of China that may not have even existed say 3 to 4 years ago.</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_35" n="35" end="timepoint_36">
<u who="RK">It&#8217;s not a straight line what had happened after the western financial crisis with China had a fit of arrogance and decided to send more you know more warships into this South China Sea to make planes to actually publish this historic map to dash line or tongue which claims you know most of the South China sea which goes against the lobs of the sea treaty and everything and this caused the reaction you know suddenly the Vietnamese and the Malaysian and others were in America&#8217;s line they all ran to America for and the Japanese who just got through Government transitions and were cool to the United nations southern embraced the United States because of this new Chinese aggression but then it seems that the Chinese back off , they seem to back off somewhat considerably keep one thing in mind there&#8217;s not nearly as much policy co-ordination in Beijing as even there is in the United States  you know the ministries you got 15 different governmental departments in ministries that deal with the South China Sea and there is not even yet from what I can gather from what they call a small leading group of top policy makers who co-ordinate grand strategy on different subjects.</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_36" n="36" end="timepoint_37">
<u>The Chinese have been making bigger in roads to Mauritius into Africa specially this just goes forward regardless of the official policy pursued by Chinese companies and it is the Chinese dig for iron ores in central southern Africa exploit for oil they find themselves getting more and more involved than the domestic politics of these countries which come back to haunt them. This all being said keep in mind that the Chinese leadership first because of the transition its going through now to a new leader but also because of the economic problems is 95% focus domestically, its focussed much greater extent domestically than any American president&#8217;s focus domestically so a lot of what we are seeing is the people&#8217;s liberation army, navy policy its policies you know of the foreign ministry and others but the top Chinese leadership is what I will give you an example when Husan Tao came to George W. Bush&#8217;s ranch 8 years ago Bush said to him what I would worry about and that keeps me up at night is a second attack like 9/11, what keeps you up at night I mean Husan Tao answered he said I have to provide 25 million more Chinese with jobs every year that&#8217;s what keeps me up at night and that&#8217;s what leadership is all focussed on.</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_37" n="37" end="timepoint_38">
<u>I think that even the Chinese navvy has different opinions I have been reading articles about this different there&#8217;s a hard line faction there&#8217;s a more moderate faction who thinks that the south China Sea is just  is a distraction, push itself or, one thing that I learned is that people and power or the elites in Beijing think of the 9-line that historical line which just drives every other country in the region today to distraction and anger that the leadership in Beijing the elites recognize that the historic line is simply unrealistic that they will have to make a compromise but the problem is that they have no domestic strategy for doing this because the nationalists are all involved in China and well China is not a democracy it has still the party to dissuade public opinion which is very nationalistic.</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_38" n="38" end="timepoint_39">
<u who="SB">Well let&#8217;s talk about India and the Indian Ocean a bit and also the convergences and the divergences in the United States and you know sort of Indians sort of positions you know when it comes to critical issues in the Indian Ocean realm . At one level it seems that there is broad convergence between India&#8217;s and US sort of perceptions you know one that both have agreed to keep the ceiling secure across the Indian Ocean and that is the major energy route of the world today and so on but there are two areas within the Indian Ocean world where India and United States have not seen eye to eye in the last few years and the present and these are of course in terms of in relation to Burma and Iran so lets you know talk about Burma on Myanmar first</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_39" n="39" end="timepoint_40">
<u>India of course constantly tried to explain to the United States that there is a need for engagement with Myanmar rather than  sanctions India had to be engaged with Myanmar partly because China was so heavily involved and India could just not withdraw and also there were connections in terms of the insurgencies in the North east and therefore however audios the regime in Myanmar might have been India felt that there was an element of real politic involved that there had to be engagement and it might seem that so far as Myanmar is concerned you know India&#8217;s position has been somewhat  vindicated that even the sort of military dictator has opened up a Burma somewhar. Earlier as I was driving today than to Boston I heard on the radio that he&#8217;s made a statement about how in fact Burma had been so closed has missed out on the opportunities that globalization had presented.</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_40" n="40" end="timepoint_41">
<u>And of course if things work out in Myanmar and there&#8217;s another country of course Bangladesh if Burma and Bangladesh are transformed then one could sort of realize that the dream that you evoked there would be a crescent from Singapore to Kolkata connected by 8 lane highways and you know through Burma and Bangladesh and both Burma and Bangladesh are rich in natural gas resources and so on so there would be connections between the Eastern part of India and the southern china through this particular sort of region so you know would you tend to agree that India&#8217;s position relating to Myanmar was in fact the right one over the last 10 years or so and this the united States also come in around to the view that things may change in Myanmar </u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_41" n="41" end="timepoint_42">
<u>In fact I was in Kolkata with Thanth minto giving a lecture on the basis of his book and he seemed to think that things look positive in terms of the opening up of political democratic processes with Ann Sun Su kyi having agreed to contest by election that on the ethnic front on the ethnic insurgencies even though there is still a very serious problem with the Gachins by and large some of the truces that have been signed holding things are somewhat better than they had been before but the main worry that Thant mint you know suggested would be how well can Burma can actually manage the opening up of the economy to a larger globalized world because there isn&#8217;t much of an expertise within Myanmar to oversee that transitions so I just wondered if you would say a few more words about Myanmar.</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_42" n="42" end="timepoint_43">
<u who="RK">I think that the Indians were right all along but at the same time Senator James of Virginia who is a South East Asian expert also agreed that the Indians were right and as soon as the Obama administration came in he kept pushing them to open up with Burma and this was before the regimes guarded changing somewhat. There is but nevertheless that India was engaged in Burma heavily in terms of real politics was very convenient for the United States because the United States can stand by half of the world away and stand on its moral principals knowing in the sense that India was balancing against China and therefore didn&#8217;t have to worry about it so to speak so there was that element but then after the Obama administration came into office there was an agreement between the Senator Web and the new Assistant secretary for state for East Asia Kurk Campbell that they would try and open with Burma and it worked and you know it seems to have worked</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_43" n="43" end="timepoint_44">
<u>You know it&#8217;s very gradual and you know it seems to be going forward the problem in Burma is that the military had been governing since 1962 there are very few people other than the military who know how to govern know how to run office&#8217;s bureaucracy&#8217;s and others so I don&#8217;t think you can have a complete transition to civilian role, you will have to have a queys eyes civilian military condominium for a number of years to keep it stable because there is very little infrastructure there its kind of a semi filled state in many regards and of course so this is a process that&#8217;s going to take years and what will facilitate it is ethnic Burman&#8217;s like Aung San Su Chi once they are elected to office can reach out to the minority groups you know all around the world and you know at the same time they don&#8217;t completely push the military area all together because the military is as audios as it has been is going to be have as a part of the story</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_44" n="44" end="timepoint_45">
<u who="SB">and certainly Aung San Su chi&#8217;s father Aung san they had quite a generous view of what you know Burman attitude should be to the non Burman minorities and it was a huge tragedy for Burma that he was assassinated in July 1947 six months before Burma came to full independence. Turning a bit to Iran but also placing it within the large Indian Ocean sort of concept how serious are the dissentions between US and Indian Policy makers when it comes to Iran there seems to be deep anxiety in some Washington circles in what India is doing to Iran India of course imports to about 10% of its oil, I would imagine 10 to 12% from Iran. India has agreed to pay for some of this oil in local currency because of the sanctions and so forth and constraints on banking transactions etc.</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_45" n="45" end="timepoint_46">
<u>India of course first of all suggests that there are these old civilizational links with Iran and that cannot be ignored you know there are important Shiya centres in India such as Luckhnow which have very close links with Shiya theological seminaries in Iran and also in Iraq by the way and India would suggest that the only land access that India has to Afghanistan at the moment is via Iran even though Pakistan has allowed some measure of transit trade and that was at the wagah border on 25th January and so there were long queue of trucks on the Indian side but of course the trucks can&#8217;t cross so there are other trucks from the Pakistani side bringing dry fruits and so on with Indian trucks with onions etc who all have to unload their cargos and in to other trucks before they can move across</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_46" n="46" end="timepoint_46 a">
<u>So you know how serious is the difference of opinion on Iran and will it affect the large Indian Ocean policy but I would also like to you know perhaps urge you to place of this whole question of Iran in to this other broader view that you expressed in your book that you know in India among strategic thinkers among policy makers such as common friend Raja Mohan there is sort of a neo curzonian  vision of what India&#8217;s role ought to be in the larger Indian Ocean world and in your book you interestingly suggested that this neo curzonian vision of a certain degree of projection of naval power in the Indian Ocean by India can in fact co exist with a Tagorian vision sort of the deployment of India the soft part by few will. </u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_46 a" n="46 a" end="timepoint_47">
<u>You know building on the age old historical links that India have had with its neighbouring regions both across the Bay of Bengal and the Arabian Sea but a sceptic might suggest that in fact the two visions the Curzonian one and the Tagorean one  are fundamentally incompatible because after all you know when Curzon went out to the on his with his naval fertile from Karachi harbour to the Persian Gulf in 1903 he got his way in the Gulf sheikdoms in Muscat and Kuwait and so on but in some ways he failed in Iran in Bush areas he didn&#8217;t get off his ship because the Iranians would not agree to his definition of sovereignty but it was in the same city Busher that Tagore received a warm and an enthusiastic welcome and India in some ways recognizes that and perhaps ceases the limits of the Curzon ian policy particularly in relation to its bigger neighbours or in its extended sort of neighbourhood so if you would address both the larger question of the Tagore ian and the Curzon ian vision  in the Indian Ocean in relation to Iran but also the US and the India sort of tussle in terms of what should be Iranian policy.</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_47" n="47" end="timepoint_48">
<u who="RK">I think you summarized it very well I don&#8217;t know what I can add, I think you as policy makers understand that India has fundamentally different intentions when it comes to, it&#8217;s national interest that is driver by geography to a significant extent remember Persian is the language is the official language of India I believe even till 1835 which is relatively recent in History that greater Persia in a cultural stand extends deep in to the Indian sub continent you can hear Persian words as far as Kolkata I believe so even just India cannot cut off Iran  I mean the links you know in Iran is a part of India&#8217;s shatter zone you know strategic shatter zone well Pakistan develops Gawadar well Iran develops Cha bahar a 150 miles away from the other side of the border and that&#8217;s kind of India&#8217;s sort of answer to Pakistan is that it helps develop this other port</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_48" n="48" end="timepoint_">
<u>India is encouraging roads that connect Afghanistan to Iran you know so that Afghanistan will have other routes to the sea and you know it&#8217;s not wholly dependent on Pakistan so that you mentioned the oil that India gets that natural gas that it wants to get Iran is just too much apart starkly and geographically of the great sub continent for India just to say all right we are going to go along with the Americans and have nothing to do with them you know that&#8217;s not just on, you know in this area action area you know Washington and New Delhi have agreed to disagree and in terms of it&#8217;s interesting in terms of Curzonian and Tagore ian vision at the very end of my book I said that the United States can only succeed great power sense if it ties its own destiny with that of the peoples of the developing world  on the Indian Ocean Rim land and so I think it&#8217;s a kind of matter of soft Curzonianism in a real way you know real politic, great powerdom is something that all nations have played and will play because nations will only struggle for survival to a certain extent and will try to calculate the balance of power in their interests you know as it affects them and that is not going away.</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_" n="" end="timepoint_48">

            </u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_48" n="48" end="timepoint_49">
<u>At the same time tough the world is getting more subtle and its getting more subtle in the way in its very Tagorian sensibility in the sense that nation and globalization national borders are less hard and you have softer borders with inter penetrations of you know ethnic groups and sectarian groups that others of quarters so you know as I wrote Tagore would have  a solution for a Kurdistan and Iraq you know he would have a solution for Afghanistan and Pakistan you know which means that borders mean less and less but people in the capital will still play a Curzonian role so to speak and especially in this global media environment like if you watch Al Jazeera what&#8217;s AlJazeera really, it&#8217;s about the rise of the middle class in the third world in the former third world if you ask me and Al Jazeerah is the television station for the rising middle class in the former third world which sees inter connection points with the other middle classes in the third world and at the same time that there&#8217;s a nationalism in power politics at play</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_49" n="49" end="timepoint_50">
<u>So at the same time,  Malaysia, Kualalumpur and Beijing can have different foreign policy that are in some ways in conflict with each other but at the same time you have a ethnic Chinese community in Malaysia  that&#8217;s connected in trade and family links with China so you have I see that if they are not compatible with Curzon ian and Tagore ian in visions or pararell they have to coexist because that is the only way to describe realistically the world that I think that we are entering a world that&#8217;s gonna continue to see you know realism and power politics and steroids between all these different States but were there are going to be these more and more inter connections at the same time.</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_50" n="50" end="timepoint_51">
<u who="SB">perhaps this is the moment to talk about before we begin to start the conversation we talk a little bit about Tagore sort of linguistic regional world and I have to say that Tagore&#8217;s 150th birth anniversary was of course celebrated in India and Bangladesh but I also attended a Tagore conferences in Peiking University in Beijing and in Singapore and in and so on and so there is a certain resonance across this entire Indian Ocean sort of world when it comes to a figure like Tagore now just wanted to talk about the Ganges delta following the way in which this project has been conceived in your book do you think in retrospect you provided a rather too pessimistic picture of Bangladesh you visited Bangladesh before the last general elections and then of course the Awami League Sheikh Hassina government came to power and in its first couple of years it seems to have been doing rather well you know Bangladesh seemed to be expressing in its politics sort of the ecumenical Islam of the India Ocean world not the dessert Islam but the Oceanic Islam  that is in fact much more widely prevalent a few of the radical sort of Islamist groups were you know clamped down upon and so on,</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_51" n="51" end="timepoint_52">
<u>you know there was an attempt to improve relations with the larger neighbour sort of India and I have been in Bangladesh twice once in January and then again in July and there it did seem to be a very sort of vibrance of civil society and educated sort of classes I was in Dhaka University for example giving a lecture in the Senate House and so forth so I just wonder whether you might want to revise your view of Bangladesh and despite all of the problems that reflected west bengal and kolkata of the poverty and the scholar and so on you gave a rather more optimistic picture of Kolkata in fact the sub title of your Kolkata chapter was the next global city and you even quoted one of your inter locuter and you said that Kolkata could be the next Harvard of that part of the world and of course I would like to believe that because you know I am engaged in trying to rejuvenate the premier education institute in Kolkata Presidency College now University trying to raise it to world class standards but should there be as much of a contrast in terms of pessimism and optimism about the future between the two Bengal&#8217;s that are divided by  the shadow lines of 1947 I just wonder what your thoughts are a couple of years beyond the publication of this book.</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_52" n="52" end="timepoint_53">
<u who="RK">Journalists are children of the moment and the moment that I was in Bangladesh they were still in military curfews and everything you know the previous civilian governments did not seceded but nobody was happy with the military things did not look well obviously they look a lot better now and I mentioned that in the sense in my afterward paperback edition that was all the room I had but clearly things look better now in Bangladesh I would agree but it&#8217;s still Bangladesh has fundamental challenges that are mainly environmental and demographic that I spoke you know briefly in the book and that are not going to go away and we are gonna have to see a sustained good government for years on it but one thing that did surprise me was that many politicians were mainly out of power and when they come back to power they don&#8217;t learn anything as if the better they were the previous time. This was the case with Benazir Bhutto I believe in Pakistan but apparently Sheikh Hassina has learnt something you know that this time there&#8217;s an they are functioning better than they did previously so maybe there&#8217;s ground for fundamental optimism in that sense.</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_53" n="53" end="timepoint_54">
<u who="SB">and of course India maybe making things a bit difficult because the promises and agreements made with Bangladesh haven&#8217;t been quite implemented or been fulfilled and too close a relationship with India without you know the concurrent benefits whether in terms of water resources and so on can be politically difficult I mean it&#8217;s the usual dynamic between a smaller neighbour and the much bigger power and of course in west Bengal there&#8217;s also been a change since you visited a 34 year old communist government since it has been voted out of power ad there are sort of new directions been sort of taken</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_54" n="54" end="timepoint_55">
<u who="RK">Bangladesh had also benefited by playing India and China against each other</u>
<u who="SB">which they are to some extent</u>
<u who="RK">yes, in terms of getting loans, grants yes and because China and India are playing a kind very low key game with each other, in Bangladesh and of course Sri Lanka obviously and these countries can benefit if they play it right.</u>
<u who="SB">and the last sort of question before I bring in the audience the very patient audience here what is your current sort of assessment sort of the Indus valley nation Pakistan at this moment and  </u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_55" n="55" end="timepoint_56">
<u who="RK">I think that I don&#8217;t think is artificial as I said, I think if you look at the history of Empires going  back to 2000 years you will find that Pakistan was always a centre of the North Western sub continent civilization of some sort and other and I don&#8217;t think that Pakistan is a failed state because it has a vibrant middle class it has some strong institutions in some regards but I think it&#8217;s the State where the militarily is invested with the conflict with India and uses that as a razon for its existence and the civilian elite you know to a significant extent are basically steel zone and pays no tax&#8217;s and that&#8217;s you know that&#8217;s a hard thing to say but it&#8217;s a reality so while it&#8217;s not a failed State it&#8217;s an extremely troubled state and the longer it engages you know in trying to manage in trying to kind of be the have defectors you know defacto control over southern and eastern Afghanistan or at least run the various terror and other ethnic networks there, the weaker Pakistan is going to get as whole together. </u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_56" n="56" end="timepoint_57">
<u>You can&#8217;t rule out the possibility of you know years and decades and several others like Punjab and Sind and Baluchistan that are oriented closer to India you know if there are going to be more weakening of State institutions as there are but I what I fear is that United States will leave gradually after Afghanistan and India and Pakistan will fight a proxy war for Afghanistan.</u>
<u who="SB">and you don&#8217;t see the possibility of some kind of a modus Vivendi being worked out between India and Pakistan about their relationship with Afghanistan.</u>
<u who="RK">I do, that&#8217;s possible</u>
<u who="SB">that&#8217;s possible </u>
<u who="RK">yes, what I fear is that there&#8217;s going to be this proxy war</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_57" n="57" end="timepoint_58">
<u who="SB">and you know I just wonder whether the larger Indian Ocean context might have helped in you know finding Pakistan a place in that larger inter regional arena and here of course India which has objected to the inclusion of Pakistan in regional organization which hasn&#8217;t really taken off when it actually should which is the Indian Ocean association you know of the Rim countries it includes all of the countries from South Africa to Indonesia including of course Oman and India of course as the hub but Pakistan is very much in Indian Ocean country and you know so a larger inclusion in broader Indian Ocean structures may in fact help matters I think</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_58" n="58" end="timepoint_59">
<u who="RK">That whole world between basically Iraq and India are in the sense part of one world you know one continue in words you know it is hard to find orders and they are united by Indian Ocean they are united by the Persian culture and it&#8217;s a matter of you know the more inter linkages confined between they are better off they will all be.</u>
<u who="SB">well Kris I think this is the moment to bring the audience into the discussion there&#8217;s a question there I think </u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_59" n="59" end="timepoint_60">
<u who="AG">Hi my name is Andy Gupta and I wanted to thank both of you to coming to fletcher to lecture today and like to speak with all of us. My question was about India and China, you mentioned that there tend to be contradictory reference where you know you have positive cultural flaws and economic flaws between the two countries but at the same time you have Governments in both capitals having   a kind of a strategic vision that might clash in the future and I was wondering how you see those relations and moving forward over the next 15 to 20 years </u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_60" n="60" end="timepoint_61">
<u who="RK">all right India and China may develop the world&#8217;s largest complementary trading relationship which will act as a cushion on their strategic rivalry with causing strategic rivalry is not any historical hatred or anything it&#8217;s really the collapse of distance brought about by advancement military technology so that you have fighter jets and military fields Chinese fighter jets that include India&#8217;s part of operations it&#8217;s why you have Indians reconaisence satelities in space focussing on China you have Indian war ships in the south China sea, Chinese war ships in the Indian Ocean there are strategic spaces overlapping so they are becoming rivals in the sense which is new in history. </u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_61" n="61" end="timepoint_62">
<u>What I find in India though is that it&#8217;s the elites who are very interested in the competition with China and it&#8217;s not a hot blooded competition or rivalry like it is with Pakistan it&#8217;s on a much lower boil and in fact I think Indian elites enjoy that because India wants to be hyphenated with China, it gives it prestige. India doesn&#8217;t want to be hyphenated with Pakistan you know the fact is that India being compared to China brings it up to a whole new level but actually India is not on that level China is far advanced its economy you know its development so you really can&#8217;t compare to I saw a statistic that showed that China adds more highways, mileage per year that India has in total in the whole country.</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_62" n="62" end="timepoint_63">
<u who="KM">Thank you very much, I have got a question about to what extent in the coming period is the lets say world history might look like in other periods that we have seen in history in the last two centuries in specific it seems that if you look at the 19th century there was a period from about 1815 to about 1880 in which one can see a kind of British world dominance that was relatively stable followed by a period from 1880 to 1945 in which you have a few like a great disorder a different type different imperial rivalries&#8217; also the rise the other part of the other side of disorder was that you had transnational connections like never before whether it was Tagore going to Persia or Teleram coming to Calcutta or there was M.N.Roy going to Mexico I mean there was that a moment in History where we saw 2 world wars but we also saw a kind of unprecedented uncapalary network of national actors communicating that seems to collapse after 1945 and produced the world that we still live in maybe the world no longer we live in because we have spoken of a post third world war era in which we started to think of area studies we started to think of 3 general domains of the world but if we are post 1989 post 2001 you describing the rise of a new world order </u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_63" n="63" end="timepoint_64">
<u>will that world order be like the period like 1880 to 1945 in which on one hand we have rising trans nationalism beyond  imperialism beyond nationalism a new kind of trans nationalism a new kind of fugitive interactions between different groups that actually is about new imaginations and communication networks or do we see also story of the 1840&#8217;s to 1945 of the world wars and is it the case that maybe we won&#8217;t have that kind of world war phenomenon because we will learn because we are historical meaning we have gone through this and so how can history really repeat itself even though we do have these what seems like structural attentions of that are inevitable in the coming you know 30,40,60,80 years so how do you see this next contour of time as we move forward in the next period.</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_64" n="64" end="timepoint_65">
<u who="RK">that&#8217;s a very good profound question of course British imperial rule was aided by the fact that Europe is mainly a piece between 1815&#8217;s and 1880&#8217;s the context because of the extension of the Mediterranean&#8217;s system and with the exception of the frank depression war which was a small war by many standards you really had the 19th century after Napoleon sent a peaceful century in continent so Britain could turn its attention somewhere elsewhere so on the wider world. I think what was, the real interesting thing that I see around the world is the rise of the middle level powers and I just don&#8217;t mean turkey and Brazil but Vietnam for instance which is a country of about 90 million people you know very strategic sea coast hard working you know a sort of mari time turkey that&#8217;s emerging so we have Vietnam, we have Turkey we have Brazil I think we are gonna see post cleric Iran in coming years that can really develop you know they could really be a magnet. </u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_65" n="65" end="timepoint_66">
<u>South Africa did not collapse as many people predicted in the 1990&#8217;s it did not collapse during the general criminal disorder so and of course the rise of these middle level powers means that least in the relative sense that United States power rises and declines in the relative sense and so then you have the new rise power China you have Germany is rising again you know the real story of this European crisis is that it&#8217;s no longer Brussels but its Berlin calling the shots and will Germany  have a new modus Vivendi with Russia in the future because Germany looks east and west and the whole point of the European Union in Nata was to keep Germany in the West but that may not have worked out but does this mean that they return to 1914 to 1945 I don&#8217;t think so because its not just people that do learn because human beings are historical its because it would be in a different era of technology the 20th century correspondence heightened the industrial revolution which would friendly the conventional military to aircraft carriers to tanks to planes etc but the later. </u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_66" n="66" end="timepoint_67">
<u>But the later middle and later 21st century is going to be comfortable you know the kinds of technologies that defeat size you know that empowers smaller groups so that the State rather than an all consuming central rise force with railway lines and tanks behind them that would allow for or allow for Hitler is going to be that all consuming and all that dominating you know in the coming decades you know we always look in the past because that is all that we know but I think the future is going to be far more subtle in terms of because people will still be divided in States, in groups so have power politics operating but they would be operating in a far more complex form then they will and i think if you would ask me what&#8217;s the biggest question in international affairs today </u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_67" n="67" end="timepoint_69">
<u>I would not say whether Iran would get new nuclear but it would attack Iran I would say that the direction of Chinese society in the economy there will can the Chinese leader one party leadership can adjust to a different growth model that&#8217;s less steep than the one in the last 30 years and organize it in a different way unless exports are driven than the one in the last 30 years and if they can&#8217;t attain power how will they distribute power you know in a you know and can it be done in a stable way because remember if you could look at China as a you know in one sense China expands out in bat to east Turkistan and to Manchuria but what if you what if Chinese economy that&#8217;s growing less suddenly more insurrection sort of in all these areas then what would you have so it&#8217;s a to me the real interesting question in world affairs boiled down to a single country is China&#8217;s domestic situation over the next 10 or 15 years </u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_69" n="69" end="timepoint_70">
<u who="C">Hi my name is Conrad and I am a student at the Tufts University here and my question is for Mr. Kaplan I am curious to see your reactions to the documents sustaining the global leadership in the 21st century that the pentagon put out in January because it represents a pretty dramatic strategic shift towards east Asia so I am curious as to what your opinions are about the strategy shift and also what the Governments on the Indian Ocean and how they are reacting to this.</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_70" n="70" end="timepoint_71">
<u who="RK">yes it&#8217;s interesting I know the person who wrote Secretary Clinton&#8217;s pivot article you know somebody has to write these things and it&#8217;s never the policy maker who gets the credit. The pivot to Asia really when you take a step back and think about it was supposed to have happened after the Berlin war though but what happened after the Berlin war it was Sadnam Hussein made his way and that&#8217;s just didn&#8217;t just tie up the US Army for the next year but it tied up the air force and the navy of the US for the next 12 years than the no fly zone and the top and then you had 9/11 and then you had the Iraq war and then the Afghan war so the US was tied up in the middle east in the land engagements and now the US is back to where it was in the 1991 so to speak it does not withdraw from the world the way it did after many previous wars with disastrous consequences </u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_71" n="71" end="timepoint_72">
<u>so rather than withdraw it&#8217;s going to do meant to do after the Berlin war fell in the first place it&#8217;s going to pivot Asia  because and it is not just about the rise of China it&#8217;s about this is the geographical centre of the world economy it&#8217;s where major shipping routes are in the world and it&#8217;s a shift to Asia that includes the Indian Ocean  and is very naval and air centric and not land centric so I don&#8217;t see there anything provocative I think it is something very natural and something which should have had happened as far back as 2 decades ago also the shift Asia is aspirational it&#8217;s not declrarational.</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_72" n="72" end="timepoint_73">
<u>It&#8217;s an aspiration rather than a declaration because it assumes that defence in the Middle East would permit and events in the Middle East never prevail. There are many you think you are finished with something in the middle east something else pops up again of course if the US attacked Iran and be an air naval operation wouldn&#8217;t be renowned for Southern operation with an occupational line  like Iraq or Afghanistan but still an attack on Iran would result in a protected naval conflict in the Gulf that could go on for months or years that could tie up an extra aircraft carrier strike to the Gulf means that it is not in Asia its in the Gulf so as I said it&#8217;s an aspiration not a declaration and it&#8217;s much more natural than people assume. </u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_73" n="73" end="timepoint_74">
<u who="Prashant">Hi my name is Prashant and I am a second year student here and thank you to both of you, my question was to shift the discussion a little bit to india and also related to the pivot question so India was part of the US strategy and then you know sort of pivot Asia and there are many administration officials talking about the more assertive role that India can play in Asia and globally as well I  sense that in new Delhi atleast in some quarters there is some reluctance to play this role that at least right now or even in the next few years there&#8217;s much more awareness and you know India&#8217;s foreign policy ambitions may take a little bit longer to manifest themselves at least on the scale that the United States may want them to but I was wondering what your impressions were about the trajectory of these ambitions and sort of scale over them.</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_74" n="74" end="timepoint_75">
<u who="RK">yes America&#8217;s relations with India cannot be transactional, it can&#8217;t be you do this and you do that the Indian body politic its history, will not stand for official treaties to treat its relations with the United States. It has to be something far more subtle and subtle in the sense that India&#8217;s rise economic and military is beneficial to itself because of where India is on the map close to China so India balances China even if it is not close to the United States so there&#8217;s no reason to push it too far or also India is the devil by land order with States with tremendous difficulty not just Pakistan but Nepal and Bangladesh as well so this depletes India&#8217;s energy somewhat on focussing outward on the outer world. India too like China is so focussed on its internal problems it&#8217;s hard to develop this you know a real robust strategic vision in that sense do you want to</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_75" n="75" end="timepoint_76">
<u who="RK">yes it&#8217;s not that India does not have that global ambition it does and I think there is an increasing realization in India that difficulty with its neighbours are necessarily hobbles you know the realization of the global ambitions and therefore over the last few years I think there has been a deliberate attempt to try and devise a new approach to neighbours in particular opening up India&#8217;s vast market to the smaller neighbours whether its Bangladesh, Srilanka or Nepal and so on and also I think what Manmohan Singh would have like to have done I think he really wanted a normalization with Pakistan and you know there are so many domestic challenges both in Pakistan and India that has quite not been realized but India does have global ambitions but these are not ambitions which will lead India to align seamlessly with United States positions in Asia or the Indian Ocean world. </u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_76" n="76" end="timepoint_77">
<u>India did go to the extent of let&#8217;s say having joint naval exercises with the United States, Singapore and Japan. India would like to see much more a polar share rather than a China dominant Asia but at the same time would not wish to be playing the US game in relation to China but as Robert was suggesting that I think Washington understands that you don&#8217;t need India to do that simply sort of a rising India is sufficient from a sort of broad sort of generous American perspective as an alternative sort of centre in Asia</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_77" n="77" end="timepoint_78">
<u>Saira Hussein:	Hello, my name is Saira Hussein and I am a first year MA candidate here in Tufts University in History, you mentioned Mr. Kaplan that if Burma opens up it could liberate north east India and I was wondering what&#8217;s the relationship of Maoism in India and North east India to the opening up of Burma and would you link the conflicts in North east India like Maoism for example to underdevelopment and isolation to be in close Burma and then thus the Indian Ocean.</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_78" n="78" end="timepoint_79">
<u>2RK:	I think partly, I think the whole Naxalite movement throughout central and Eastern India and the Maoist movement in Nepal and these tendencies in the North East India are partly a consequence of isolation and under development because you know these groups that are cut off from the outside world to a certain degree and Maoism is not associated with 60million people Mao tongue would have killed in the great leap forward and the you know the great revolution culture and others you know it&#8217;s just it&#8217;s kind of a slogan against isolation a slogan against underdevelopment a slogan against the powerful from those who are disfranchised so to speak and I think that&#8217;s what comes from no ultimately and, but we should not minimize this movement, it&#8217;s amazing how resilient it has been over the decades you know it&#8217;s I mean  China may be a few years away debating Mao&#8217;s legacy you know it&#8217;s reasonable to assume 10 years or so Maoists will picture may not hang over to the you know as the debate develops about Mao but through the whole swath of the sub continent you know movements that call themselves Maoists or who are all like Mao&#8217;s managed to survive because of poverty and underdevelopment.</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_79" n="79" end="timepoint_80">
<u who="SB">you know I would just add that I entirely agree with Robert that it is poverty and underdevelopment that really you know underlies the Maoist insurgencies in India but you have to recognize that there is a you know there is a distinction to be made being Maoism now in the tribal heartlands of Northern and Central India from the southern borders of Nepal through Bihar, Jharkhand, Chattisgarh the fringes of West Bengal then Orissa and all the way down to Andhra Pradesh and that is quite different from the kinds of disaffections that you see in North eastern India which are mostly you know regional insurgencies which have suffered a different kind of exclusion from you know from India&#8217;s development story 79</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_80" n="80" end="timepoint_81">
<u>so I would just emphasize the distinction between what is going on in North Central sort of India that heartland and the North east of India and also Maoism has gone through different phases I mean it started in sort of West Bengal and the late 60&#8217;s during the height of cultural revolution and Mao had hailed the naxal bari uprising in a small village in Northern west Bengal as they spring thunder of the Indian revolution but unfortunately for Mao it did not spread like a up reary fire and so but I remember the days as we were growing up in Calcutta and we were high school students you know all the walls of Calcutta with posters saying China&#8217;s Chairman is our chairman now that phase has passed but Maoism you know as an inspiration for particularly marginalized tribal people&#8217;s you know continues to have some force did you have a question?</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_81" n="81" end="timepoint_82">
<u who="Mediah">Hello, My name is Madeeah, I am also a History student here at Tufts I was wondering if you could comment on Gawadar a bit more on the way you see that port city coming up if you were bothered to be secured especially like of China coming in to more power on the Indian Ocean Rim in the next 20or 30 years as you said.</u>
<u who="RK">Yes, Qatar has a great location and it&#8217;s an incredible port to look at sea because it is the super modern Chinese built port right literary in the middle of the 19th century setting because the town itself despite all the billboard it&#8217;s about condos and the luxury hotels is still pretty it&#8217;s about off the beaten path and as underdeveloped as you can imagine.</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_82" n="82" end="timepoint_83">
<u>It&#8217;s really something write out of wilfred thesiger travels in Arabia in the 1950&#8217;s before big oil came but Gawadar is undefended you know if the Chinese have had a naval base there they would have the Indians breathing down there neck so I don&#8217;t see it as a Chinese naval base what I see it as is if Pakistan were ever to stabilize and Afghanistan too then I could see the Chinese extending their road building projects from the quaracorms north right through the Gawadar in order to take oil and natural gas from Africa and elsewhere in the Middle East, the ship into North and western China to avoid the straight of Malaka and that of course would lead to tremendous developments one of the problems in Gawadar is that I could talk on my book is these incredible lands game where land is been stolen from the local people by corrupt elites you know in Karachi and Lahore and that has raised the spectrum even further Baluchi nationalism which as frightened off  the Chinese. </u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_83" n="83" end="timepoint_84">
<u>I think the reason cause remember I think it was a year ago or so it was after Bin laden was killed and Pakistani&#8217;s wanted to get back at the Us so the Pakistanis defence Minister was in Beijing and saying that Chinese are going to build ys the naval base there and then 2 days later the Chinese defence minister said oh no we are not you know which was pretty much a rebuke and anything that you can imagine. I think Gawadar is a long term prospect for the Chinese they built the port they let the Singaporeans run it but then they are not going any further with it at this point, not like the ports in Burma&#8217;s and Sri Lanka.</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_84" n="84" end="timepoint_85">
<u who="Deriah">Hi, My name is Deriah, I am an admin person at Harvard Kennedey school, i also do research for the Middle east studies there and I want to thank you both for a very fascinating conversation and I wanted to ask sort of a left handed question for either or both of you and I don&#8217;t point one of you just unable to connect it at all you began the presentation sort of contrast in strategy sort of what does one do with strategy how one devises a strategy devising of strategy verses building concepts conceptual sort of understanding of this part of the world and it strikes me that the confluence of strategy and concepts might be affix sort of an ethical understanding of how one behaves in the world it&#8217;s such that the world would be a better place and I was wondering with respect particularly to the Indian Ocean to the Oceanic part of this conversation that we are having is that there is something Oceanic in that part of the world that could sort of further or has furthered has helped people&#8217;s to gain a more ethical understanding over time to sort of learn from mistakes strategic mistakes to build maybe longer term vision ahead of what should be happening really of the sort that I am hearing from you I mean I hear a very something on the way to an ethical understanding of the some of the national interests and some of the decisions that are made and I was just wondering if you could sort of talk a little further on it.</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_85" n="85" end="timepoint_86">
<u who="RK">Well, I think part of the ethical understanding is going from a great power based military based feud to a more legal feud you know if you consult things legally or rather than through force or intimidation that&#8217;s more ethical and you know I just came back from Singapore and Malaysia where I got a lot of rethink on the law of the sea traders relates to the South China Sea and one of the things that I learned is that China signed the law of the Sea trading but does not adhere to it whereas the United States never signed it but does adhere to it that the law of the sea trading kind of partially leads way out of the military crisis and territorial crisis of the South China Sea.</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_86" n="86" end="timepoint_88">
<u>I say partially because everyone benefits from the law of the sea claims except China because China gets nowhere with the law of the Sea because 200 miles south it&#8217;s easy it&#8217;s just in the middle of the Ocean whereas Vietnam, Philippines, Malaysia they go to 200 miles they get all these oil rich islanad to china and so to speak so even the law of Sea trading which is probably the furthest that nations have gone in terms of practically applying ethics in a great power sense is not foolproof it does not provide an equitable solution for all parties because China would not go along with it because you know the geography for China is just isn&#8217;t there so but I think Sugata would want to say more about it because the Oceans are commons a world commons we all have to get along with them in one sense and that kind of points towards ethnic ness. </u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_88" n="88" end="timepoint_89">
<u who="SB">and also I think the ethical literature so far as it addresses the question of legitimacy good governments and so on historically circulated entirely across this inter regional arena of the Indian Ocean if you think about the Aklakkh literature the aklakhi nursery or the aklakhi jalali you know coming out of the Arab and the Persian world&#8217;s but actually circulating for centuries later all across sort of India so there is a concern about ethics about what is good governance what is legitimate governance and so on you know that is shared across this inter regional arena and again if you think about the eastern Indian  ocean the Raj Chakravarty idea which underpins a notion of layered and shared sovereignty that was so important before you know the nation State idea that got infringed in this part of the world that too circulates all across the eastern Indian Ocean you know it includes what today is Indonesia, the Malay world, Thailand, Burma and India and if you think about Tagore&#8217;s journeys across the Indian Ocean in some ways he is suggesting that we should not let colonial borders and he&#8217;s also anticipating national borders constrict our sort of imagination our search for connections and there is a bit of strategic essentializing that he is doing </u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_89" n="89" end="timepoint_84">
<u>And now it&#8217;s not as if the pre modern Indian Ocean arena had certain kinds of connections had certain kind of ethical aspirations but that does not mean that there was no military conflict in that period we should not romanticize that period just to give you one example a thousand years ago the 1020&#8217;s there were the Cholas from the southern India who inflicted a very major naval defeat on the srivijaya empire that&#8217;s centred on Sumatra Ok and the same in the same decade the Cholas sent up an land army  defeated the palas of Bengal and brought two Bengali princesses from the holy water Ganga to concentrate the new capital of the Cholas called Gangai chola puram now </u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_84" n="84" end="timepoint_85">
<u>when i was in Singapore a few years ago I was asked to release a new book on the Chola voyages to south east Asia and of course I said that this is very ironic to get a Bengali you know to release this book on the Chola voyages because the Rajendra Chola had defeated both the Srivijaya Kingdom and the Pala Kingdom of Bengal but when Tagore went to South east Asia he underplayed these episodes of military conflict or aggression and in some ways they were exceptions rather than the rule and decided to put the spotlight on trade on economic connections on a common cultural acumen that connected this larger Indian Ocean world suggesting  that you know that is the more ethical way of behaving in the present and proceeding in the future so that&#8217;s the way I think the ethics of the Oceanic realm sort of come in to play and retain some relevance in today&#8217;s world, yeah..</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_85" n="85" end="timepoint_86">
<u who="SB">I think these should be the last 2 questions and they need to be brief because well let&#8217;s take with permission of the Chair Kris let&#8217;s take three quick brief pointed questions together and then let&#8217;s give Robert the last word and then Kris you be the last one </u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_86" n="86" end="timepoint_87">
<u who="John">Hi my name is john and I am a new grad at Tufts and thanks for coming to Tufts and talking to us. You mentioned earlier that  you think  that Pakistan is not an artificial nation and but also that there&#8217;s between Iraq and India there&#8217;s this very difficult to know where to draw the borders because of this sort of the shared persian culture that runs across this whole region so accepting the premise that Pakistan is not an artificial nation I think there can be agreement  there can be a that on the durand landline is a very artificial boundary and so bearing in mind how difficult is to tell often times when the federal minister tribal areas of Pakistan ending and an Afghanistan begins if Pakistan not taking such an active role in tribal parts as in Afghanistan is contingent to their stabilization and their overcoming their structural problems within Pakistan, how can what kind of solution could allow Pakistan to disengage from Afghanistan if it&#8217;s so difficult to say to tell the pashtune culture of the areas various end in Afghanistan </u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_87" n="87" end="timepoint_88">
<u who="RK">Pakistan can never disengage from Afghanistan without coming to some sort of agreement with India because what drives Pakistan into Afghanistan is because of its insecurity over India because it feels the needs are Islamic based which to confront India  so I think ultimately this solution to what laid diplomat Richard Holbrooke called back is between Pakistan and India. </u>
<u who="Asad">Hi my name is Asad and thank you so much for coming here, I had a question in the 20th century the country that was trying to get to the Indian Ocean was Russia and you still is that dream or is that ambition over with especially if the arctic icecap is also melting in North and I just want to know what you think about it.</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_88" n="88" end="timepoint_89">
<u who="RK">Well, Russia would like not to give up on the dream but I don&#8217;t see where Russia has any practical you know has any practical where with the world to accomplish it any more. Russia can barely get control of its all near abroad and the Soviet Union and Central Asia because it&#8217;s been bordered with the Chinese by their money by the South Koreans and other actors in Central Asia so I think well the days when Russia was on the border of Afghanistan breathing down Afghanistan&#8217;s neck are long past at this point in time. Russia will have enough of challenge holding up its influence in the former Soviet Central Asia. </u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_89" n="89" end="timepoint_90">
<u who="Harish">Hi, my name is Harish and I am a fresh student at this University and as you mentioned earlier about your program in Kolkata you know I am a Kolkata resident and I am closely trying to follow your internship program there my question is how&#8217;s your membership program ever considered to change the admission policy of Presidency University or the other Universities in west Bengal just the way we have here in US which doesn&#8217;t only considers numbers but also the other parts of the application? </u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_90" n="90" end="timepoint_91">
<u who="SB">I will talk to you at a greater length about this question later but let me just yes we are trying to put in place completely new ways of recruiting faculty and completely new ways of bringing students and actually being rather proactive you know a centre of excellence also has to reach out to talented students who might be in the most backward districts of the country and so forth but the current challenge is to make sure that all current faculty appointments to be made on the basis of academic merit alone and therefore there are 184 faculty positions that have been advertised the deadline was yesterday the 29th of February more than 5,000 applications have come in and there are high powered selection committees of the best people in each discipline and in  the field who are going to be making these appointments </u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_91" n="91" end="timepoint_92">
<u>And just to bring the story back to the Indian Ocean world Presidency University historically was a colonial institution and therefore the History curriculum that I had to follow focussed exclusively on Indian History and on European History with papers like you know they were good but 5th century BC Greece Teward and Steward Britain, Modern Europe from the French Revolution, International relations with Europe with a completely different focus. One way with which we are trying to change the curriculum for the new students is to have much greater emphasis on the neighbouring regions and the opportunity to study the history and politics of China, Japan, south East Asia, west Asia you know Iran, the Arab world and so on, Tagore did that in his University, Shanti Niketan promoting the study of China and Japan but this did not occur in what were in those days colonial institutions and that colonial hangover lasted into the 1970&#8217;s when I was an under graduate in Presidency College but we are going to give even the curriculum in Presidency and the Indian Ocean orientation if you like.</u>
</u>
            <u rend="transcript_chunk" start="timepoint_92" n="92" end="timepoint_end">
<u who="Kris">Thank you very much and I think that is actually a very fitting question on which to end partly because both of our panels both Robert and Sugata have spoken about the idea about the Indian soft power have both spoken about the idea of bringing Curzon and Tagore together and one way in which that way has happened historically is through higher education and the development of you know the institutions of cultural politics and its fascinating that even the way that you know Tufts and Harvard are connected to that and of course Sugata being on the mentors group here at Tufts we have a very cutting edge project co teaching a class with LUMS University in the hall where Ayesha  is currently you know that in Johannesburg Wits University is expanding currently and kind of its research to focus on Africa and sub continental Indian connections Singapore University Dhaka University and so forth really there is a flourishing going on and I think that speaks to some of the flourishing of new politics new hydro carbons are out so forth that are certainly aspirational and I  like the distinction between the aspirational and the declaration so that is a very fascinating point to make so if I had much to think about and it leaves me only now to thank both of our panellists Robert Kaplan and Sugata Bose for the stimulating discussion and conversation Thank You.</u>
<u who="RK">Thank You very much.</u>
</u>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>